Guide to the Falkener Family Papers, 1893-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Falkener Family papers 1893-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Falkener family.
9.0 linear feet Extent: 7000 Items
African-American family based in Greensboro (Guildford Co.), North Carolina. Waldo C. Falkener served on the Greensboro City Council from 1959-1963. His wife, Margaret, was also politically active. The collection primarily documents the political career of Waldo C. Falkener, and comprises minutes and reports from Greensboro City Council meetings. There are also materials from his campaigns for office and items that document his successes as a council member. In addition, there are documents relating to other family members, including photographs, news articles, correspondence, and deeds. Later accessions include clippings, correspondence, and other materials documenting the political careers of the Falkeners. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
RL.00379
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Please consult the Detailed Description below and the Collection Control File.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Falkener Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift, beginning in 1996.
Biographical Note
Waldo and Margaret Falkener were descendents from a well-established African-American family based in Greensboro (Guildford Co.), North Carolina. The Falkener family was involved in the Ohio abolitionist and underground railroad movements during the Civil War. Through the late nineteenth and twentieth centuries, they were active lawyers, teachers, and community leaders.
Waldo C. Falkener, a black civil rights activist in Greensboro, first began lobbying the city for equal rights in the 1940s. His demand for African Americans to have access to Greensboro's public golf courses led to the city's closing the courses in 1949. Falkener was elected to the Greensboro City Council in 1959, and was the only black member of the Greensboro City Council during the 1960 Woolworth's lunch counter sit-ins. While on the council, Falkener pursued better roads, public utilities, recreational facilities, and more public employment. After his second term, Falkener worked as a bail bondsmen and real estate developer. He died in 1992 at age 89.
His wife, Margaret Evelyn Evans Falkener, was born in 1919 to Robert and Lillie Evans of Salisbury, North Carolina. She attended Talladega College in Alabama, graduating in 1940. Margaret and Waldo married on January 23, 1942, and eventually had three children. Along with her husband, Margaret was also politically active in the Democratic Party, and was a member of numerous civic groups in Greensboro, including the AKA Sorority, Greensboro United Way, Greensboro Girl Scouts, Jack and Jill of America, Inc, and The Girlfriends. Margaret Falkener died in 2004.
Waldo Falkener's parents were active community members in central North Carolina. His mother, Margaret Mitchell Falkener, was born in 1870 in Oberlin, Ohio. She attended Oberlin College, moved to North Carolina to teach, and married Henry Hall Falkener in 1892. Henry Falkener was born in Warren City and attended Shaw University in Raleigh, North Carolina. He was a schoolteacher in the 1880s. He was elected to the North Carolina State Senate and served from January to March 1889 as a representative of Warren County. Following his term, a new North Carolina law requiring a poll tax and literacy test for all voters went into effect, essentially ending the black vote and any chance for his re-election. (It was 80 years before another black representative was elected to North Carolina's state government.) After 1889, he worked at the newly established A&M College for the Colored Race (now North Carolina A&T) as a bursar, librarian, and English professor. Meanwhile, Margaret Mitchell Falkener founded the music department at A&M College in 1894, where she taught piano. She later became the first woman supervisor of Guilford County's black schools. Margaret was an organizing member of Unified Institutional Baptist Church, a founder of the county's first black garden club, and was a member of the Federation of Colored Women's Clubs of North Carolina. They had five sons, including Waldo.
Margaret Mitchell Falkener's younger brother, George Henry Mitchell, was born in Washington, D.C., in 1875, and grew up in Chattanooga, Tennessee. He attended Shaw University for a Bachelor of Laws in 1899, and then went to University of New York for his Master of Laws. He was admitted to the North Carolina bar in 1900, and moved to Greensboro in 1902. George Henry Mitchell was the first black attorney in Greensboro, and became the first president of the North Carolina Negro Bar Association. Along with his law career, Falkener was a real estate developer and published a weekly paper, The Carolina Patriot, with William Windsor. He married his first wife, Maude M. Wood, in 1903; they had one son, George Junior. Maude died in 1907. George Mitchell later married Lucy C. Smith, of Chattanooga, and they had five children.
Margaret and George Mitchell's father, George W. Mitchell, was a professor of Latin and Greek at Howard University. He also practiced law. Their mother, Alvira Scott, was the daughter of abolitionist John H. Scott, of Oberlin, Ohio. Scott was active in Oberlin's anti-slavery movement, and at one point had led a protest at a jail to free 15 of Oberlin's black residents who had been called before the U.S. District Court to answer charges of infringment of Fugitive Slave Laws. He also attended Oberlin College.
Collection Overview
The collection (1996-0025) (2325 items, dated 1893-1996) primarily documents the political career of Waldo C. Falkener, and comprises minutes and reports from Greensboro City Council meetings. The council minutes include committee reports (finance, public works, transportation, and real estate committees), as well as ordinances, laws, memoranda, and letters. There are also materials from his campaigns for office and items that document his successes as a council member. In addition, there are documents relating to other family members, including photographs, news articles, correspondence, and deeds.
Addition (1996-0180) (75 items, dated 1959-1992) contains clippings, programs, reports, letters, photographs, and notes.
Addition (1999-0482) (4500 items, dated 1893-1996) contains personal, family, and business papers and correspondence documenting the Falkeners' life experiences and careers, as well as those of other family members.
Addition (2001-0099) (50 items, 0.1 linear feet; dated ca. 1959-2001 and n.d.) includes correspondence, obituaries, and newspaper articles further documenting Waldo Falkener's political work and his involvement in the civil rights movement in the Greensboro community. In addition there is correspondence relating to the life of Falkener's father, Henry Hall Falkener, also an active politician and public school teacher (ca. 1961-2001).
Addition (2001-0121) (50 items, 0.1 linear feet; dated 1960-1979) contains correspondence and newspaper articles received by Waldo Falkener or about Falkener during his term as Greensboro City Councilman and his re-election campaign (1960-1961). Also includes newspaper articles about Falkener's civic services and letters of appreciation (1972, 1979), as well as materials related to the successful campaign to name a Greensboro school after Falkener and his father (2001).
Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Falkener family; Falkener, Waldo; Falkener, Margaret; Minority business enterprises -- United States; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Greensboro; African Americans -- Political activity -- Southern States; African American business enterprises; African American business people; African Americans -- Correspondence; African American women -- Political activity; Civil rights -- North Carolina -- Greensboro; Greensboro (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Clippings; Photographs; Deeds; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Accession (1999-0482), 1893-1996, (4 boxes)
  Accessions 1996-0025 and 1996-0180 are included in this series description. This material includes some RESTRICTED items relating to Waldo Falkener's activities as a bondsman. Please consult the Collection Control File.
  - Falkener Family (Box 1)
    - The Falkener Family: Portrait of Black Civic Leadership from the Mid-1800s to the Present (Box 1)
    - News articles about the family (Box 1)
  - George H. Falkener
    - Prince Hall Masons (Box 1)
  - Henry Hall Falkener
    - North Carolina A&T College (Box 1)
    - Deed, 1895 (Box 1)
    - Mortgage, 1896 (Box 1)
  - Madge Z. Mitchell Falkener
    - News article about her (Box 1)
  - Margaret E. Falkener
    - Biographical sketch (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Programs she participated in (Box 1)
    - Bob Jordan for Governor campaign (Box 1)
    - Centennial planning committee (Box 1)
    - Democratic party correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1972 Democratic National Convention (Box 1)
    - Finding Funding Conference, Sept. 17-19, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Frank Holder Dance Co. 10th Anniversary Gala (Box 1)
    - Greensboro Historic District Commission (Box 1)
    - Greensboro Historical Museum (Box 1)
    - Girlfriends (Box 1)
    - NC Museum of History (Box 1)
    - YWCA (Box 1)
    - Programs, general (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Waldo C. Falkener
    - In Memorium (Box 1)
    - News articles about him (Box 1)
    - Programs he participated in (Box 1)
    - Awards: Greensboro Men's Club, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Name badges (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Greeting cards (Box 1)
    - Campaign materials (Box 1)
    - Campaign materials, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Campaign materials, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Campaign materials, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Campaign materials, 1963, testimonial dinner, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Campaign materials, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Financial papers--cancelled checks (Box 1)
    - American Federal Savings and Loan Association (Box 1)
    - American Municipal Association, 1959 (Box 1)
    - American Municipal Association, 1961 (Box 1)
    - American Municipal Congress, 1961 (Box 1)
    - American Municipal Congress, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Black firefighters (Box 1)
    - Bond maker, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      Access is RESTRICTED. Patrons must sign a waiver to use these materials.
    - Conference of community leaders on Equal Employment Opportunity (Box 1)
    - Door sign (Box 1)
    - Greensboro City Council, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Greensboro Planning Board, 1966 (retain street name: Dudley Street) (Box 1)
    - Segregated golf facilities (Box 1)
    - West African visitors, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Programs (Box 1)
  - City Council Meeting Agendas, (19 envelopes, 1 folder) (Box 1)
    Includes agendas, minutes to be approved, planning documents and proposals, and commission reports for Greensboro City Council meetings. Also included are copies of the United States Municipal News, a newsletter by the U.S. Council of Mayors outlining municipal progress for the period.
  - City Council Meeting Agendas, cont., (54 envelopes, 1 folder) (Box 2)
  - City Council Meeting Agendas, cont., (35 envelopes, 6 folders) (Box 3)
  - City Council Meeting Agendas, cont., (12 envelopes, 6 folders) (Box 4)
  - Printed Materials
    - Textile Labor (Box 4)
    - Public Management (Box 4)
    - Popular Government (Box 4)
    - Misc. reports, (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - Handbook on Boards and Commissions of the City of Greensboro, 1961? (Box 4)
    - Misc., 1959 (Box 4)
    - Pamphlet No. 7, 1963 Advance Legislative Service to the General Statutes of North Carolina (Box 4)
    - Proceedings of the American Municipal Congress, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Columbia University Bulletin 61, No. 7, February 18, 1961, Summer Session 1961 (Box 4)
- Accession (2001-0099), 1959-2001 and undated, (1 folder)
  The addition (2001-0099) (50 items, 0.1 linear feet; dated ca. 1959-2001 and n.d.) includes correspondence, obituaries, and newspaper articles further documenting Waldo Falkener's political work and his involvement in the Civil Rights movement in the Greensboro community. There is also correspondence relating to the life of Falkener's father, Henry Hall Falkener, an active politician and public school teacher (ca. 1961-2001).
  - Waldo Falkener and Henry Hall Falkener materials (Box 4, Folder Acc. 01-099: 1)
- Accession (2001-0121), 1960-1979, (1 folder)
  The addition (2001-0121) (50 items, 0.1 linear feet; dated 1960-1979) contains correspondence and newspaper articles received by Waldo Falkener or about Falkener during his term as Greensboro City Councilman and his re-election campaign (1960-1961). Also includes newspaper articles about Falkener's civic services and letters of appreciation (1972, 1979), as well as materials related to the successful campaign to name a Greensboro school after Falkener and his father (2001).
  - Waldo Falkener materials (Box 4, Folder Acc. 01-121: 1)